I'm Dr.. Jordan B. [Peterson] a pSychology professor of the University of Toronto and Canada
I'm going to tell you the story behind the self authoring Suite Website.
A few years ago, I realized that the students in my classes had written essays on all sorts of subjects in grade school and college
However, they'd never been asked to write thoughtfully about themselves about their own past experiences
personalities and visions for their futures.
Upon reflection
This lack of opportunity struck me as strange to say the least
Since there's nothing more important to get straight than your own personal experience.
At the same time I was speaking with managers at various companies about how to hire more effective workers
They were much more interested in how to improve the performance of poorly performing people they had already hired.
I didn't have much to tell them at the time because improving people is very difficult. Nonetheless the two problems stuck in my mind.
So I started to search for psychological interventions that could be used widely and practically to clarify and improve people's lives.
I already knew that people lived inside the stories they told about themselves and that they used those stories to interpret everything around them.
While considering this I came upon, Dr. James Pennebaker's research
conducted at the University of Texas at Austin.
Dr. Pennebaker tested Sigmund Freud's theory that the release of emotions related to traumatic events could be curative.
He had his students write for three days for 15 minutes a day about the most upsetting experiences of their lives
while a control group wrote about ordinary daily activities.
Those in the former group experienced long-term improvements in their psychological and physical health after a brief dip in mood
Not so much because of the expression of pent-up feelings however
But because they drew more specific causal conclusions
About what had happened to them in the past.
Dr. Laura King had her subjects write about their ideals and future goals instead, but they experienced the same benefits.
Our research team specifically tested the effects of the future authoring program part of the self authoring suite related to goal setting
at McGill University in Montreal Canada and Erasmus University in Rotterdam, Holland.
Academically struggling McGill students increased their grades by
25% in one year and decreased their dropout rates from 30% to zero
the same thing happened at Erasmus University
with more than 1,200 business students.
These effects do not just apply to students either
Dr. Frank Schmidt, one of the world's outstanding industrial psychologists, has demonstrated that participating in such programs
Makes all kinds of people substantially more effective or whatever they are doing
People who complete such programs appear to benefit because the careful articulation of their experiences, past, present and future
decreases misery related to threat and uncertainty and
Increases happiness and hope which people experience when they progress towards somewhere they truly want to be
When complicated experiences are carefully put into words the manner in which they are represented in the brain changes
They move from the areas associated with stressful emotion demanding constant physical readiness
To the areas associated with detailed comprehension and understanding
This makes articulate people less stressed and more
informed about how to be successful now and in the future
It is for these reasons that we developed the Self Authoring Suite a set of four
interactive online writing programs and are offering them to anyone who wants to concentrate on improving his or her life.
If you want to understand yourself better
Become less anxious and happier and commit yourself more firmly to your education career or your relationships
these programs will help
a lot
Each of the programs is composed of a series of interactive web pages that present you with specific personal questions
This simplifies and guides the difficult process of personal writing
Each program requires careful thought and takes several hours to complete
It is better to write over a number of days so that you have time to think and because sleep aids the process
The writing is challenging, but the experimentally documented benefits are worth it
The past authoring program helps you write an autobiography. It will present you with pages like this introducing you to the program
And providing psychologically sound advice and information
It will then ask you to start writing dividing your life into seven epochs or sections and describing the important experiences of each
The two present are three programs help you address your personality faults and capitalize on your virtues
When you start either of these programs you will also be presented with instruction pages
Then you'll be provided with a list of adjectives some of which will accurately define you and be asked to select six to nine
Describing your faults if you're feeling up to a challenge
Or your virtues if you could use a boost
You will then be asked to rank order these adjectives and to write a paragraph
describing a time when each had a specific effect on your life the future authoring program
Helps you define the future that would work best for you
Three to five Years down the road and just as importantly to describe the future you want to avoid
It starts with some questions like these which will start you thinking in the right direction
then it will ask you to write freely about what you want and don't want and about how to justify your decisions
and stay on the right track
The programs contain much more detail than this brief summary presents
Here are the sorts of additional questions you will be asked to consider
What were your 10 most important experiences?
Where they positive or negative?
How did each experience change you or your view of other people?
Were there things that you should have done differently?
Are you the life of the party do you feel comfortable around people?
Do you think before you act?
Are you full of ideas? Are you a sensible person?
Do you do things according to a plan?
Are you too quiet around strangers?
Do daydream too much?
What is one thing that you could do better?
What do you want to learn about?
How should you handle your drinking or drug use?
Describe your ideal social life
You may choose to complete any or all of the four programs
You will be given a confidential username and account password and your writing will be securely stored
Once you have completed each program you'll receive an organized comprehensive email laying out the work that you have done
You can return to the programs in the future to edit and update your work
Many people do not understand who they are where they are or where they are going
In consequence instead of attempting those actions that would make their lives as valuable as possible
things just happen to them
and they're often not good
Carefully answering all the questions in the Self Authoring Suite in your own words will clear the fog from your vision
make you healthier and stronger
and increase the chances that you will exist in a manner that justifies all the trouble that life inevitably presents
This will help you be a good person for yourself and for other people
Carve yourself a new and better you
There's no sense slouching around miserably when you can aim for what you should have and get it
Good luck with the programs